# Valerie Russell

Email: vruss14@gmail.com | Phone Number: (313) 241-0774 | Location: Detroit, Michigan

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/valerie-russell-732731162

Portfolio: https://github.com/vruss14/web-development-portfolio | GitHub: https://github.com/vruss14

## **SUMMARY**

Front-end web developer with a bachelor's of science in human biology, as well as certificates in search engine optimization and editing. Currently working towards a certification in full-stack web development. Because of my experiences as an editor, I am especially passionate about debugging and refactoring code to produce deliverables that are both fully functional and easy to maintain.

## **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Languages: HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript

Technologies and Other Skills: Git, GitHub, jQuery, Bootstrap, AJAX, Responsive Design

## **PROJECTS**

DinGen | https://github.com/ellisaissa/DinGen-Web | https://ellisaissa.github.io/DinGen-Web/

Dinner generator that leverages data from public, third-party APIs that helps users find new recipes

Tools: HTML5, CSS3, Tailwind, JavaScript, jQuery

Coding Quiz | https://github.com/vruss14/coding-quiz | https://vruss14.github.io/coding-quiz/

Multiple choice quiz on front-end programming built with HTML5, CSS3, and JavaScript

 $\textbf{Weather App} \mid \underline{\text{https://github.com/vruss14/weather-forecast-dashboard}} \mid \underline{\text{https://vruss14.github.io/weather-forecast-dashboard}} \mid \underline{\text{https://v$ 

• Provides forecasts by fetching data from the OpenWeather API; built with HTML5, CSS3, and JavaScript

## **EXPERIENCE**

#### **Crisis Text Line, Volunteer Crisis Counselor (Remote)**

Jun 2020 - Present

• First-line responder to help texters through empathetic listening; 128 hours volunteered and 131 conversations total

#### **Proofed, Editor and Proofreader (Remote)**

Jun 2020 - Jan 2021

• Copyedited and proofread for corporate and academic clients; experience with editing grant applications and dissertations

### Rev.com, Transcriptionist (East Lansing, MI)

Dec 2017 - Jul 2018; Jun 2020 - Aug 2020

Wrote and edited transcripts for clients in medical, business, and education industries; 6100 minutes of content transcribed

## **EDUCATION**

#### Coding Bootcamp (Full-Stack Web Development), Michigan State University, (Remote)

Jan 2021 - Present

• Comprehensive certification course in front-end and back-end web development

## The Fundamentals of Digital Marketing Certificate, Google Digital Garage (Remote)

Nov 2020

Trained in SEO and SEM optimization, interpreting analytics, and creating successful ad campaigns on all platforms

### **Editing and Proofreading Certificate, Proofreading Academy (Remote)**

Apr 2020 - May 2020

• Trained to edit and proofread documents according to Harvard, APA, MLA, Chicago, and IEEE style guidelines

#### Bachelor's of Science in Human Biology, Michigan State University (East Lansing, MI)

Aug 2014 – May 2018

• GPA 3.74; Dean's List (min. GPA 3.5) every semester; 2017 Reetz Family Scholarship recipient; Honors College member